JAMIE CRAANE

SR FULLSTACK SOFTWARE ENGINEER

Contact

06 4337 9507 jcraane@gmail.com

github.com/jcraane twitter.com/jcraane jcraane.blogspot.com rxpatterns.com/ know-it.nl/

Top skills

Software development Android Kotlin multiplatform AWS

Education

Avans University of Applied Sciences, 1997 -2001

ABOUT

I have been developing software professionally since 2001. Helping customers with solutions that really add value. I like a challenge and continuously keep my knowledge up to date and share it with great enthusiasm to the public and with my team.

Since 2012 I have been designing and developing backend and mobile applications for organisations with user bases of several hundred of thousands to millions of users. From high performance backend systems which run on AWS to native Android apps for consumers.

I am always looking to try out new things to find out how these can be used to advance new and existing solutions.

EXPERIENCE

Android Kotlin Native developer, Eneco, Feb 2019 - present

Architected and developed the new Eneco app from the ground up by using a state of the art architecture using Kotlin Muliplatform Mobile (KMM) which is used by hundred of thousands of users.

By using KMM we are able to deliver an exceptional native user experience and still share a lot of code between Android and iOS. By using libraries like Ktor, coroutines, kotlinx-serialization and Klock we are able to share the following code across the two platforms:

Networking, caching and persistence

Serialization

Error handling

Business logic

Viewmodels

Localizations and images

By using continuous delivery and automated tests we are able to release new features quickly and reliable.

Native Android software engineer and AWS cloud architect, Dutch railways, 2013 - 2019

Developed the native NS Android App for the Dutch Railways including most of the backend systems the app uses. The NS App is the official app from the Dutch Railways with over 5 million users. UI designs were always implemented with pixel perfect precision.

To facilitate fast response times and high availability at all times we architected and implemented the backend systems the app uses natively on AWS. Because we were responsible for the reliability, performance and availability of the systems ourselves, everything was highly automated and

tested (with still a focus to keep costs under control).

Developed several unique services which the app uses like auto-complete for various types of locations using Elastic Search including geo location search.

Used Flutter to create a specialized app for the deaf and partially sighted people.

All knowledge was shared within the organization so other departments like the NS website could also use the services developed for the app.

Software engineer, Timewax, 2013 - present

Designed and developed a drag & drop template designer in Javascript which allows customers to interactively create a template for invoices that are sent by customers. Developed several backend systems which are used by this and several other frontend components.

Developed the native Android app which I later migrated to Kotlin Multi Platform Mobile so the iOS app could also use the same shared code as the Android app.

SIDE PROJECTS

- Android developer, TransIP Stack app, 2019
- Android developer Simpled card, 2017
- Android developer, Limbi, 2017

CERTIFICATIONS AND COURSES

- Machine Learning, Coursera, 2019 (holding certification)
- AWS Certified Architect Associate, 2019 (holding certification)
- AWS Certified Developer Associate, 2018 (holding certification)
- AWS Cost Control
- AWS Cloud Formation
- AWS Security Specialty

PUBLICATIONS AND PUBLIC SPEAKER EVENTS

- Innovative apps in public transport, J-Fall 2015,
- Developing web applications with Vaadin, Java Magazine 2011, https://release.nl/magazines/Aveq/118665.pdf
- Genetic algorithms with JGAP, Java Magazine 2009, https://biplatform.nl/magazines/Aveq/115903.pdf
- iBatis, J-Spring 2011